<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" 
    xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
    xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
    xmlns:admin="http://webns.net/mvcb/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/dtds/podcast-1.0.dtd">
	<channel>
<title>Earl Baker&#x27;s Weblog</title><link>http://earlbaker.com/index.html</link><description>Earl&#x27;s Thoughts</description><dc:language>en</dc:language><dc:creator>earl@earlbaker.com</dc:creator><dc:rights>Copyright 2010 Earl Baker</dc:rights><dc:date>2013-04-13T22:08:47-04:00</dc:date><admin:generatorAgent rdf:resource="http://www.realmacsoftware.com/" />
<admin:errorReportsTo rdf:resource="mailto:earl@earlbaker.com" /><sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
<sy:updateBase>2000-01-01T12:00+00:00</sy:updateBase>
<lastBuildDate>Sat, 22 May 2010 11:43:58 -0400</lastBuildDate><item><title>Fix the Debt</title><dc:creator>earl@earlbaker.com</dc:creator><category>Politics</category><dc:date>2013-04-13T22:08:47-04:00</dc:date><link>http://earlbaker.com/blog/files/fix-the-debt.php#unique-entry-id-3</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://earlbaker.com/blog/files/fix-the-debt.php#unique-entry-id-3</guid><content:encoded><![CDATA[Having served at local, county and state levels of government in the Commonwealth of Pennsylvania, I feel I have a pretty good understanding of the need for fiscal responsibility in the public sector.   It is vital that each type and function of government operate within its means.   I was known in public service for working toward an efficient, effective and responsive government that would also always be fiscally responsible. 


So it is natural that the idea of being fiscally responsible at the national level should be subjected to the same principle.   As a nation we have repeatedly ignored or delayed our obligation to address the national debt and it has become a serious issue.   Policy makers, the press and the public always seem to assume &ldquo;somebody will figure this out and do something about it.&rdquo;   So far that has not happened!   If we don&rsquo;t take immediate steps to corral this problem, we could be looking at a major economic crisis in the very near future. 


Over the past several years, the national debt has skyrocketed to unsustainable heights.   If we continue on our current course of inaction, we will enable economic turmoil both here in Pennsylvania and across the entire nation, and it will reduce our leadership role in the world.   This mountain of debt is already crowding out funding for our most important domestic programs such as education and infrastructure development, as we continue to make annual interest payments of nearly $500 billion.   We cannot afford to service this bloated debt at the expense of neglecting the nation&rsquo;s most important needs.   We don&rsquo;t lack for ideas such as the Simpson-Bowles Commission and it is ironic indeed that those who appointed it did not find it politically palatable to accept their recommendations. 


I was pleased when our elected leaders in Washington announced they had reached a deal to avoid the fiscal cliff at the 11th hour, but as they say, &ldquo;the devil is in the details.&rdquo; 


When I began to read through the specifics of the agreement that averted the cliff, I was truly disappointed.   We knew the fiscal cliff was coming for more than a year and still were not able to address the root causes of the debt.   The deal did generate over $600 billion in new revenue relative to current policy, and it did manage to save &ndash; at least for the time being &ndash; over 78,000 thousand jobs for Pennsylvanians.   But the deal did not include a substantive agreement that bends down the trajectory of our debt. 


Each side is firmly entrenched in its respective position and seemingly unwilling to give an inch on any of the policies and programs that are important to them.   Republicans refuse to acquiesce on more revenue and Democrats avoid discussing spending cuts.   Tax policy reform, which both parties claim to favor, is discussed but is not given sustained attention. 


This is a truly dangerous stalemate given the rapidly approaching deadlines for the debt ceiling (mid-


February or early March), the budget sequester (March 1), and the expiration of the Continuing Resolution &ndash; the legislation that allows our government to function (March 27).   Each of these fiscal events represents an opportunity while also acting as a deadline.   They each offer a chance for lawmakers to examine ways we can rein in wasteful spending.   They also provide a forum for discussions on how we can reform entitlements so that they&rsquo;re effective for those that need them most, and measures we can take to reform our tax code to make it more globally competitive while raising additional revenue for the government.   This sort of robust approach is the only way to properly tackle our debt problem, thereby ensuring a prosperous future for Pennsylvanians and the entire nation. 


I am encouraged by the fact that there are people out there focused on ensuring lawmakers are engaging in thoughtful, substantive negotiations focused on bending down the trajectory of the debt.   One such group is the Campaign to Fix the Debt, a nonpartisan group dedicated to placing America on a more responsible fiscal course.   The campaign has assembled a diverse array of business and policy experts, former members of Congress, and over 340,000 concerned citizens.   I would encourage you to visit FixTheDebt.org to learn more about this effort and sign the Campaign&rsquo;s Citizen&rsquo;s Petition. 


The coming weeks and months will be critical for our state and the country.   We have the chance to make great strides towards restoring order to our fiscal house.   Let&rsquo;s seize this opportunity &ndash; let&rsquo;s fix the debt! 
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Lincoln</title><dc:creator>earl@earlbaker.com</dc:creator><category>History</category><dc:date>2012-01-23T19:50:32-05:00</dc:date><link>http://earlbaker.com/blog/files/lincoln.php#unique-entry-id-2</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://earlbaker.com/blog/files/lincoln.php#unique-entry-id-2</guid><content:encoded><![CDATA[I recently had the opportunity to participate in a seminar with Professor Harry Jaffa, one of the foremost writers and thinkers on the subject of liberty in our era. 


He is the author of the influential "Crisis of the House Divided" which concerns Lincoln and the critical period of the Civil War.    Here he is joined by me with my friend, the Director of the Ryan Center at Villanova University, Dr. Colleen Sheehan.    The Center keeps alive issues of liberty looked at from a Constitutional point of view.
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Churchill</title><dc:creator>earl@earlbaker.com</dc:creator><category>History</category><dc:date>2011-04-26T20:33:51-04:00</dc:date><link>http://earlbaker.com/blog/files/churchill.php#unique-entry-id-1</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://earlbaker.com/blog/files/churchill.php#unique-entry-id-1</guid><content:encoded><![CDATA[Admirers of Winston Churchill gathered recently in Charleston, South Carolina.    It was actually not because it was the 150th anniversary of the shot at Fort Sumter which started the Civil War, which was coincidental, but because when Churchill was hit by a car in New York in 1932. (he looked the wrong way the same way we do when we go to Britain)  Bernard Baruch offered him the opportunity to recuperate at the Hobcaw Barony near Charleston.    Baruch had assembled 16 plantations on the Charleston estuary as a hunting preserve and it was a great chance for Churchill to regain his strength in the home there.  


Attending the conference was Churchill&rsquo;s great grandson Randolph, shown here with me and with Allen Packwood, Director of the Churchill archives at Churchill College, Cambridge.    While most assembled historians and Churchill experts agree one cannot project the views and attitudes of Churchill from the past on to later situations, in any exact way, it is generally agreed and I agree that his message of gathering and analyzing intelligence, preparing for challenges to democracy that may arise in the future, and a concern for the health of the private economy are all matters at issue today.


We are fortunate that the Churchill Centre keeps the memory alive of Winston Churchill, the man who led England through its tortuous year alone keeping Western Civilization from crumbling before Hitler and the Nazis, and brings together people who want to know more about him, his works, and his legacy.]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Federalism</title><dc:creator>earl@earlbaker.com</dc:creator><category>Politics</category><category>History</category><dc:date>2010-09-02T21:08:22-04:00</dc:date><link>http://earlbaker.com/blog/files/federalism.php#unique-entry-id-0</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://earlbaker.com/blog/files/federalism.php#unique-entry-id-0</guid><content:encoded><![CDATA[Since I was a poly sci professor interested in the topic of &ldquo;federalism&rdquo; for many years, it was a real thrill to see that a colleague and acquaintance of mine from that period of my career, Elinor Ostrom of Indiana University, had been awarded the Nobel Prize in Economics earlier this year.


The idea of overlapping jurisdictions and shared governance has always fascinated me whether as a teacher and writer in the field, or a practitioner within the political system at several &ldquo;levels.&rdquo;


 


I  believe William Penn had that sort of vision when he founded the Commonwealth of Pennsylvania in 1682 (and it has led a lot of people to be concerned ever since that our system of local government isn&rsquo;t neat, orderly or more tidy).    Elinor and her husband Vince have worked for years in the field of &ldquo;political economy&rdquo; to show that people working together at the local level are generally more efficient and more responsive than when a &ldquo;top-down, one size fits all&rdquo; approach is used to deal with community issues.


 


After hearing she received this Prize, which not only pleased me but also surprised me because the prevailing ideology in academe is hardly favorable to Elinor&rsquo;s non-statist writings, I was further happy to be invited to attend a Symposium with her at Lafayette College in Easton by my long time associate and friend, federalism scholar John Kincaid, shortly after her receipt of the Prize.    (The photo is of Nobel Laureate Elinor Ostrom.     Joining her with me are professors Ben Schuster, John Kincaid and Conrad Weiler.    John is the Director of the Meyner Center at Lafayette.)


 


Her simple and humble presentation of her research was refreshing.    With a strong belief in the power of individuals to act in their own and their community&rsquo;s best interest in cooperation with others at the local level, Elinor described the Nepalese farmers among whom her research was conducted.    She told how their decision making was done in mutuality with their fellow farmers, and how the professional quality of their water control decisions was superior to those in top down control situations.    I am sure I am not doing all her laborious research justice in this brief description, but that is the essence of it and it is compelling&hellip;and obviously the judges thought her (and her longtime colleague-husband&rsquo;s) lifetime  of substantial work should be recognized.    Please visit her website for further information about the Ostroms and their many academic contributions to understanding how a multiple level, &ldquo;federal,&rdquo; form of government as our Constitution provides, works in a democracy.
]]></content:encoded></item></channel>
</rss>